<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Amrit's Blog (Posts about nlp)</title><link>https://example.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://example.com/categories/nlp.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:mail.amritpandey@sap.com"&gt;Amrit&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 19:06:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Prompt Engineering: Crafting response from LLMs</title><link>https://example.com/posts/prompt-engineering/</link><dc:creator>Amrit</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In year 2023, news like &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jodiecook/2023/07/12/ai-prompt-engineers-earn-300k-salaries-heres-how-to-learn-the-skill-for-free/?sh=54fc9c309d4a"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; popped nearly everywhere claiming that there is a new job in the field of AI and it pays as high as $300k a year. On careful examination I found out that even though this job had "engineering" in it's title, it has actually nothing to do with engineering. But prompt engineering is a skill that if mastered well may not end you a $300k job but will give you wings when it comes to generating correct responses from an AI Large Language Model like GPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every industry today is using an LLM for their practical purpose or has plan to use it productively. But why LLMs are so popular? It is simply because for the first time AI models can effectively generate good amount of text/response that can be productively used. Almost all the LLM models works on QA model i.e. one where you ask a question and model generates an answer based on your question. However the task of framing a question can be as simple as writing few lines to writing a well structured essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI models have evolved a lot where they can successfully generate bouts of text that are extremely accurate however they haven't evolved enough to understand the context and the hidden meaning behind a human's need. For example, you may ask LLM "Generate a recipe for evening beverage", to this LLM would respond with a list of instruction for a hot cup of mocha. But what if, the user wants "hot" beverage that is catered to indian cuisine. Also, instead of generating list of instruction, you want it to generate the instructions in paragraph.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><category>llm</category><category>nlp</category><guid>https://example.com/posts/prompt-engineering/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 18:49:58 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>